So this section
is about object-oriented programming,
and this lecture is gonna be
a very general, high level overview
of this programming paradigm.
So we're gonna talk about
what object-oriented programming is,
how it works in general,
and about its four fundamental principles.
So this is gonna be a really important
and valuable lecture.
And so let's get started.
So, first of all, what is object-oriented programming?
Well, object-oriented programming,
or OOP in short,
is a programming paradigm that is based
on the concept of objects.
And paradigm simply means
the style of the code,
so the how we write and organize code.
Now we use objects to model,
so to describe aspects of the real world,
like a user or a to-do list item,
or even more abstract features
like an HTML component
or some kind of data structure.
Now, as we already know, objects can contain data,
which we call properties, and also code,
which we call methods.
So we can say that by using objects,
we pack all the data
and the corresponding behavior
all into one big block.
So again, that's data and corresponding behavior.
And this makes it super easy
to act directly on the data.
And speaking of blocks,
that's exactly what objects are supposed to be.
So in OOP, which is the acronym
that I'm gonna use instead of object-oriented programming.
Okay.
So in OOP objects are self-contained pieces of code
or blocks of code,
like small applications on their own.
And we then use these objects
as building blocks of our applications
and make objects interact with one another.
Now these interactions happen
through a so-called public interface,
which we also call API.
This interface is basically a bunch of methods
that a code outside of the objects
can access and that we use to communicate
with the object.
Okay.
So let's take a breath here
because this all sounds kind of abstract, right?
But don't worry.
It will make more sense
once we start developing these concepts
using code throughout this section.
But anyway, why does OOP actually exist?
Well, this paradigm was developed
with the goal of organizing code,
so to make it more flexible
and easier to maintain.
So before OOP, we might have a bunch of codes
gathered across multiple functions,
or even in the global scope
without any structure.
And this particular like crazy style of code
is what we usually call spaghetti code
and spaghetti code makes it very hard
to maintain large code bases
and let alone, add new functionalities to it.
So the idea of OOP was basically created
as a solution to this problem.
And apparently it worked because today,
OOP is probably the most popular
and most widely used programming paradigm
in large scale software engineering.
Now, OOP is certainly not the only way
of writing organized and maintainable code.
So in fact, there're many other paradigms
that have become increasingly popular
and one of them is functional programming.
And functional programming allows us
to achieve the exact same goal
of basically avoiding spaghetti code.
And as I have been saying,
we will talk about functional programming
later in the course and compare it
with object-oriented programming.
But for now, let's focus on OOP.
Now, actually using objects
is nothing new for us at this point, right?
We have been using them all the time.
However, up until now,
we have basically only used objects
as loose collections of data
and without making them interact with one another.
Also, we didn't have a way
to generate objects programmatically.
All we ever did was using simple object literals,
but in OOP, we actually need a way to generate,
so to create, new objects from our code.
And to do that in traditional OOP,
we use something called classes.
You can think of a class as a blueprint,
which can then be used to create new objects
based on the rules described in the class.
So it's just like an architecture
where the architect develops a blueprint
to exactly plan and describe a house.
But the blueprint is really just an abstract plan,
like a set of rules,
but nothing tangible that you can actually touch.
However, from that blueprint,
many real houses can then be built
in the real world.
And with classes it's just the same.
So let's take a look at this fictional user class
as an example.
And I say fictional
because this is not actual JavaScript syntax.
Okay.
Because JavaScript does not actually support
real classes like I'm explaining here.
We do have a class syntax in JavaScript too,
but it still works a bit differently
from what I'm gonna show you here.
However, the idea of creating objects
from a kind of blueprint
is still a very useful mental model to have.
Because in general terms,
this is still how OOP works
across all languages
and that includes JavaScript.
And so that's the reason
why I'm showing you this here,
so as a conceptual overview,
and for you to have this as a mental model.
But anyway, back to our fictional class here,
we can see that it kind of describes a user
who has a username, a password, and an email.
So it's a description of data about a user,
but it's not the data itself yet.
Because remember, the class is really just a plan
and a plan doesn't contain the real world data just yet.
On the other hand, we then have the behavior
that is associated with the data.
And in this case,
that's just a login method
and a method to send messages.
So just like we learned in the last slide,
this class has everything related to a user.
So data and behavior
all packed into one nice, self-contained block.
But now let's use this class
and actually create a new object
from this class.
And you see that now we actually have
real data about the user and the object
and not just a description of the data
like we have in the class, so in the plan.
Now we call all objects created through a class
instances of that class.
So again, an instance is a real object
that we can use in our code,
which was created from a class,
and a class itself is not an object.
All right.
So back to the blueprint analogy from earlier,
this instance is like a real house,
which was created from the abstract blueprint
created by the architect.
And the beauty of this is that now
we can use this class to create as many instances
as we need in our application.
Just like we can build multiple houses
from just one blueprint, right?
And all of these instances,
so these objects, of course can have
different data in them,
but they all share the same functionality,
which is to login and to send messages.
Okay.
So now we know that we can create classes
to generate objects from these classes.
So we know how classes work,
but the next logical question is,
how do we actually design a class?
Or in other words,
how do we actually model
real-world data into classes?
So these questions are just
like an architecture student asking,
well, how do we actually plan
and design a house?
And that's of course a very good question.
Now the answer is, as you can imagine,
not straightforward.
So there is not a single correct way
of designing classes.
There are, however, four fundamental principles
that can guide us toward a good class implementation.
And these principles are abstraction, encapsulation,
inheritance, and polymorphism.
And these are actually techniques
that can also be used outside of OOP,
but they are especially relevant in this context.
So let's now take a more detailed look at each of them.
And the first one is abstraction.
And abstraction basically means
to ignore or to hide details
that don't matter.
This allows us to get an overview perspective
of whatever it is that we're implementing
instead of messing with details
that don't really matter to our implementation.
So let's say that we're implementing a phone
for a user to use.
And even though this doesn't make much sense in code,
it's still a great example and analogy.
So without abstraction
we could design our class
to include everything that there is about the phone,
including all the internal stuff
like verifying the phone's temperature and voltage,
turning on the vibration motor or the speaker,
and other low-level details.
But as a user interacting with a phone,
do we really need all of this detail?
Well, I guess not.
Right?
So in reality, when we interact with a real phone,
all of these details have been abstracted away
from us as the user.
And all that we're left with is a simple phone
that we basically only interact with
using the home button,
volume buttons and the screen.
Everything else is gone
because we simply don't need it as a user.
So the phone then operates kind of as a black box,
without us seeing what is happening inside.
Now, of course, internally
the phone still needs to vibrate
and to measure the voltage
or to turn on the speaker,
but we can hide these details from the user.
And that is exactly what abstraction means.
Now, going back to the example
of a user from the last slide,
we could implement a user's phone number,
mailing address, hair color, shoe size,
and tons of other stuff
that we might not need in our application.
So we simply ignore these details.
Now, abstraction is really important,
not just in OOP,
but in programming in general.
In fact, we create and use abstractions
all the time.
For example, take the add event listener function
that we use all the time.
Do we actually know how exactly it works
behind the scenes?
Well, we don't.
And do we care?
No, not really.
Right?
And we don't have to because once more,
the low-level details of how exactly it works
has been abstracted away from us.
We are simply the user.
And so we can simply use that function
without completely understanding it
and without having to implement it ourselves.
So that's abstraction,
which actually blends in with the next principle,
which is encapsulation.
And encapsulation basically means
to keep some properties
and methods private inside the class
so that they're not accessible
from outside the class.
However, some methods can, of course,
be exposed as a public interface,
which we call API.
And this is exactly what I meant
at the beginning of the lecture
when I said that interactions between objects
happen through a public interface.
And going back to our example of a user from before,
this is what private properties
might look like conceptually.
And again, I'm talking hypothetical here
because this private keyword here
actually does not exist in JavaScript.
But anyway, as we already know,
outside code now can't access these properties.
However, inside the class,
they are still accessible.
For example, the password is, of course, necessary
in the login method, right?
And so there we can use it.
And by having these critical properties
nicely encapsulated like this,
we prevent external code
from accidentally manipulating this internal state.
And by the way, the term state simply refers
to an object's data.
Okay.
Anyway, this is really important
because allowing external code
to manipulate internal state directly
can cause many kinds of bugs,
especially in large code bases
and developer teams.
Now, as you see, there's also a private method here,
the check spam method.
Again, it's not accessible from outside a class,
but it's used internally
to check if a comment is spam or not.
So we want no one else outside of the class
to be able to use this method,
and so basically we don't make it
part of the public interface.
So the public interface
is essentially all the methods
that are not private,
so that are not encapsulated.
So making methods private
makes it easier for us to change our code
without breaking code from the outside,
which might rely on some of these methods.
For example, if the check spam method was public,
then it could be used anywhere in our code.
And if we then changed the implementation of the method,
it might break that code that is relying on it.
So again, this helps avoiding bugs
and also spaghetti code.
And really this is not just some theory,
this is a real practical scenario.
Alright.
So there is a real reason why encapsulation
and private methods and properties exist.
So in summary, we should always have the goal
to nicely encapsulate most of our state and methods
and only leaving essential methods public
for the reasons that I just explained.
Next up, we have inheritance.
So let's say we have these two classes,
user and admin,
which stands for administrator.
And as we can see, they have actually
a lot in common.
In fact, admin has all the properties
and methods that user has.
Right?
And that actually makes sense
because if you think about it,
an admin is also a user.
So an admin also needs a password and an email,
and he also needs to log in, for example.
However, if we design our classes like this,
so as two separate identities,
we will end up with a lot of duplicate code
and we already know that that's bad.
Right?
But well, that's where inheritance
comes into play.
So in OOP, when we have two classes
that are closely related,
like user and admin here,
we can have one class inherit from the other.
So we will have one parent class
and one child class, and the child class
then extends the parent class.
Okay, great.
But what does all of that actually mean?
Well, it's actually quite intuitive, I think.
So just like you as a child
probably inherited some features of your parents,
a child class inherits all the properties
and methods from its parent class.
Now, in more formal terms,
inheritance makes all properties and methods
of a certain class available to a child class,
which of course then forms a hierarchy
between these two classes.
And the goal of this is to reuse logic
that is common to both of the classes.
In this case, both the admin
and the user need to log in.
And so instead of writing that logic twice,
it makes sense to inherit the login method
from the more global class,
which is the parent class user,
to the more specific class,
which is the child class admin.
Now of course a child class can then also have
its own methods and properties.
So at the end of the day,
the child class ends up with some methods
and properties from its parent
and some of its own.
So we can say that the admin is also a user,
but basically an extended user,
so with some added functionality.
Okay.
And finally, the last principle is polymorphism.
And polymorphism sounds a bit weird,
which is because it comes from Greek,
where it literally means "many shapes".
Now, in the context of OOP,
in simple terms, polymorphism means
that a child class can overwrite a method
that it inherited from a parent class.
And here are our user and admin classes again.
But now we also have a third class,
which is the author.
Now admin and author are both
really just special kinds of users,
and so it makes sense that they both inherit
from the user class,
just like we studied in the last slide.
Therefore, they inherit all the properties
and methods from the user class,
but we're gonna focus on the login method now.
Now let's say that an admin requires
a different kind of login method.
For example, a more secure one,
which has two-factor authentication.
And let's say that we also need
a special login method for authors.
So how do we give them different login methods?
Well, it's actually quite simple.
In each class we simply just write a new method,
which is also called login.
And then, according to polymorphism,
that login method will overwrite
the login method that has been inherited
from the user class.
And that's actually it.
That's all you need to know about polymorphism.
And actually that wraps up this introduction
to object-oriented programming.
So I know there was a lot to take in here,
so make sure to understand everything
before actually moving on in this section.
Now, next up, we're gonna talk about
how object-oriented programming
actually looks like in JavaScript.
Because, as I said in the beginning,
it is implemented in a bit different way
from what I explained here in the beginning
with classes and instances.
It's still crucial to understand that,
but again, in the next video,
we will see how JavaScript does it.